<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An arrow shot against Babylon out of Josephs bow which grew up from the stem of Jesse ... and this is a visitation and warning (once more) from God unto all such rulers, teachers, and people in England who are, or may be persecutors about religion and worship that they may yet flee out of Babylon ... the great whore (which hath set upon nations and reigned over the kings of the earth) that they may partake no longer of her sins ... and this may serve as a glass for all false Christendom to behold themselves ... / by William Bayly.</title>
            <author>Bayly, William, d. 1675.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1663</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 66 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A27119</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B1518</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25910</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09288343</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09288343</idno>
            <idno type="VID">42614</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A27119)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 42614)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1301:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An arrow shot against Babylon out of Josephs bow which grew up from the stem of Jesse ... and this is a visitation and warning (once more) from God unto all such rulers, teachers, and people in England who are, or may be persecutors about religion and worship that they may yet flee out of Babylon ... the great whore (which hath set upon nations and reigned over the kings of the earth) that they may partake no longer of her sins ... and this may serve as a glass for all false Christendom to behold themselves ... / by William Bayly.</title>
                  <author>Bayly, William, d. 1675.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>26 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1663.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Persecution.</term>
               <term>Freedom of religion.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:42614:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ARROVV SHOT AGAINST BABYLON OUT OF Joſephs Bow,</p>
            <p>Which grew up from the ſtem of <hi>Jeſſe,</hi> the Root and Off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring of <hi>David,</hi> (and was bent by the Archer of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which hath ſtruck at <hi>Cains mark,</hi> from Paradice into the Land of <hi>Nod,</hi> and hath lighted in the <hi>skirts</hi> of the <hi>great Whore,</hi> to the diſcovering the Mother (or original) of <hi>Harlots</hi> and all <hi>Abominations</hi> of the <hi>Earth;</hi> tracing her in her footſteps (with all her <hi>Companions</hi> and <hi>Merchants,</hi> the <hi>Beaſt, Dragon</hi> and <hi>falſe Prophet</hi>) by the <hi>blood</hi> of the <hi>Prophets</hi> and <hi>Saints,</hi> and of all that were <hi>ſlain</hi> upon the <hi>Earth</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And alſo purſuing her from her <hi>birth</hi> (or the Serpents hole) out of which ſhe came, to her <hi>latter end,</hi> which is the <hi>bottomleſs pit,</hi> or <hi>Lake</hi> of <hi>Fire</hi> into which ſhe muſt <hi>return.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this is a <hi>Viſitation</hi> and <hi>Warning</hi> (once more) <hi>from God,</hi> unto all ſuch <hi>Rulers, Teachers</hi> and people in <hi>England</hi> who are, or may be <hi>perſecutors</hi> about <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>VVorſhip,</hi> that they may yet flee out of <hi>Babylon</hi> (myſtery <hi>Babylon</hi>) the <hi>great VVhore</hi> (which hath ſet upon <hi>Nations,</hi> and reigned over the <hi>King of the earth</hi>) that they may partake no longer of her <hi>ſins,</hi> leſt they partake of her perpetual <hi>plagues,</hi> which cometh ſwiftly upon her in one day.</p>
            <p>With a few queſtions concerning the <hi>Devil,</hi> and <hi>Cain,</hi> and the <hi>Whore,</hi> and the <hi>Dragon,</hi> and the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> and <hi>falſe Prophet,</hi> whence they came, and where they are, and how they may be known, and whither they muſt all go together in the end.</p>
            <p>And this may ſerve as a Glaſs for all falſe Chriſtendom to behold themſelves, and try their ways, and ſee what Spirit and Church they are of, and whoſe children they are; <hi>if ye were Abrahams children, ye would do the works of Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> WILLIAM BAYLY.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Put your ſelves in array againſt Babylon round about, all ye that bend the Bow, ſhoot at her, ſpare no arrows for ſhe hath ſinned againſt the Lord,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Jer 50.14.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>For thy Merchants were the great men of the earth; for by thy ſorceries were all Nations deceived, &amp; in her was found the blood of the Prophets &amp; of ſaints, and of all that were ſlain upon the earth,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Rev. 18.23, 24.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year 1663.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:42614:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:42614:2"/>
            <head>An <hi>Arrow</hi> ſhot againſt <hi>Babylon,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>IN the beginning (before tranſgreſſion) man was in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radice, the Garden of God, made in his own image and likeneſs, and was in unity and peace with him, in the innocent, meek, tender, holy, upright life, in which he was formed; in which ſtate he ſtood with God, as a Child with a Father, or as a Wife with a Husband, without va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riance, diſtance or enmity between them, and God's bleſſings was upon them in this their innocent, lowly, obedient ſtate, till at length another ſpirit got an entrance by deſiring (or let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the deſire go out after the eye) to be more knowing and wiſe in the myſteries of the outward Creation and viſible things, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which ſoon captivated the tender, ſimple, upright mind, and beguiled it from its own proper life and being, in which it was made a living ſoul; for they did not only taſte, but eat, and that brought the death over them, as it is written <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.17. for they entred into a ſecret falſe joy of what they had attained to, and a ſatisfaction they got in the ſenſual wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and knowledge of things, and ſo grew conceited that they were as Gods, knowing good and evil, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And ſo through this aſpiring ſpirit (or motion) which began to ſpring up in their minds, a ſecret ſtrife or enmity began to ariſe between the innocent life and it; for there was a contrariety between them; but they <hi>eat</hi> of the Tree of <hi>Knowledge,</hi> which <hi>beguil'd</hi> them from the Tree of <hi>Life</hi> in the midſt of the Paradice of God. This was <hi>Adam</hi>'s fall, going outward with his mind from the gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, rule and dominion of the innocent, upright Life, by which he was made a living ſoul, feeding in the aſpectings and viewings of the viſible things, the myſterie and ſecrets of which was hid (from him) in that Life from which he was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted, and he only could retain but ſtrong imaginations of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:42614:3"/>them, which puſt him up; ſo now he became a griever and an oppreſſor of God's good Spirit, and it became a reprover and troubler of him by reaſon of his diſobedience againſt it, and departure from it, and he was now afraid of God's voice, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving done that which was contrary to him; and then to get peace, he ſewed fig-leaves to make themſelves coverings, but all would not do while the Tree of knowledge is fed upon, (which was good in its place, but forbidden to feed upon) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it beguiled from the Tree of Life, being pleaſant to the eye, and deſirable to make one wiſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (and the World by Wiſdom knows not God) ſo by it they loſt the knowledge, and unity, and peace of God, and were driven into the Earth, and ſhut out of the Paradice of God, and became vailed in the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, pride and pleaſures of the Earthly or ſenſual part; which followed that aſpiring motion of the ſubtil Serpent or Adulterer that led out from God, like the Harlot <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks of, that was ſubtil of heart, whom the young man fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, as an Ox to the ſlaughter, and as a fool to the correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Stocks, and knew not that it was for his life, and that her paths led to the Chambers of death, and her ſteps take hold of Hell; this is the thing: <hi>Adam</hi> was very young, and the Harlot ſubtil, ſo was deceived; for the one enticed, and the other conſented and followed, not knowing it was for his life, though God had ſaid he ſhould ſurely dye; but this Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter led out the mind from the ſence of the good man of the Houſe, with her Bed of pleaſures and delights, and with enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing vvords ſhe forced him, but the end was bitter as Worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, as hath been known by woful experience; for here was the firſt carrying away captive into <hi>Babylon,</hi> the <hi>Myſterie</hi> (of which the <hi>outward</hi> vvas but a figure) and the firſt draught of the Whores Cup of Fornication was novv drunk, by vvhich the juſt innocent life ſuffered (as one might ſay) even in the Womb, and in <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abel</hi> the tvvo Seeds or Spirits were clearly manifeſt, the one in pride, fury, enmity, murther, drinking his brothers blood; and the other the ſufferer by him (in the patience) vvhoſe blood had a voice that cryed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God from the ground; and yet it's ſaid of <hi>Babylon,</hi> that in her is found the blood of the Martyrs and Prophets, and of <hi>all</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:42614:3"/>the <hi>Saints</hi> that have been <hi>ſlain</hi> upon the <hi>Earth</hi> (then <hi>Cain</hi> was in <hi>Babylon</hi>) which is now called the <hi>Great Whore;</hi> and the contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie between <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abel</hi> was about <hi>Sacrifice</hi> and <hi>Worſhip;</hi> this hath ſpread (even the Spirit of Whoredoms, Enmity and Wickedneſs) over the World, and <hi>Cains Mark</hi> hath been apparent among multitudes, peoples, tongues and languages, <hi>killing</hi> and <hi>perſecuting</hi> about <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Worſhip:</hi> This is the [great] <hi>Whore</hi> which hath ſate upon [many] Waters, &amp; reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed over the <hi>Kings</hi> of the <hi>Earth,</hi> over multitudes, tongues, peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple's and languages, they are the <hi>Waters, Rev.</hi> 17.15. on which the <hi>Whore</hi> ſits, the unſtable people, in the unſtable ſtate, toſſing up and down in confuſion, reſtleſs, full of ſtirs (a tumulcuous City) theſe are the <hi>Waters,</hi> the <hi>ſwelling,</hi> the <hi>roaring,</hi> the <hi>foaming,</hi> the <hi>toſſing;</hi> the <hi>[Wicked]</hi> are like the troubled <hi>[Sea]</hi> which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not reſt, whoſe Waves caſt up mire and dirt; and there is no peace to the [Wicked] ſaith my God; theſe are the <hi>[Waters]</hi> on which the <hi>[Whore]</hi> ſits; this was <hi>Cains</hi> ſtate (who had drunk the Whores Cup, and killed the Juſt about ſacrifice) drove from God, a Vagabond, no peace, but great puniſhment, grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than he could bear; and the Wicked foam out their own ſhame, like the raging ſea, drunk with the Cup of the Mother of Harlots and all abominations of the Earth; then mad up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their idols (as the Prophet ſaid) perſecuting and killing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout VVorſhip and Sacrifice: This hath been the ſtate of the Drunkards of <hi>Ephraim</hi> in all ages; this is <hi>Cains</hi> way, and the <hi>Whores</hi> way, which is become <hi>great,</hi> and have <hi>reigned</hi> over Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Tongues, Multitudes and Peoples, and Kings of the Earth; <hi>Babylon [Myſterie Babylon]</hi> the original of All Abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, and Mother of Harlots, riding upon a <hi>ſcarlet</hi> colour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Beaſt,</hi> full of Names of Blaſphemy, deckt with Gold and Purple, Pearls and precious ſtones, having a golden Cup in her hand, but its full of abominations and filthineſs, and ſhe is drunken vvith the blood of the Saints and Martyrs of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, and the beaſt is ſcarlet coloured vvhich carrieth her, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving horns, [mark that] the Povvers of the Earth, Kings and Rulers have been made drunk vvith her Cup, and have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted fornication vvith her, and ſhe hath ſate and reigned o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them, and the beaſt hath carried the VVhore, and they
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:42614:4"/>have made war with the Lamb and the Saints, and killed them; this is <hi>Cains</hi> way, vagabond from God, in wrath and envy, whored from God, killing about Worſhip and Sacrifice, killing juſt <hi>Abel,</hi> killing the Prophets, Saints and Martyrs of Jeſus. This Whore hath ſate and reigned upon Tongues Multitudes, Peoples and Kings of the Earth. This is the <hi>great Whore</hi> that hath glorified her ſelf in her <hi>abominations,</hi> ſitting as a Queen, ſaying in her <hi>heart,</hi> ſhe ſhall never ſee <hi>ſorrow, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this is the Vine of <hi>Sodom,</hi> her grapes are grapes of abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations; through the ſpreading of her boughs, the whole earth hath been corrupted, and by her dominion the Lamb hath been ſlain, blood hath cryed againſt her from the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the World, even from <hi>Abel</hi> to this day, the Land of uprightneſs hath mourned while the wicked have born rule, and lamentation hath dwelt upon the Tabernacle of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, darkneſs hath covered the earth, and groſs darkneſs the people; death and deſtruction hath reigned, the Devil (the Murtherer from the beginning) hath been the God of the World for ages and generations, and the true God hath been unknown, and his appearances a Myſterie hid from them, and a Covenant hath been made with death, and an agreement with Hell, and man hath been ſeparated and driven from God as far as the Eaſt is from the Weſt, and the abomination which maketh deſolate hath ſtood where it ought not; iniquity hath abounded, and love hath waxt cold; the whole World hath been like a Wilderneſs, wickedneſs hath ſate in the Ephah, and unrighteouſneſs in the Judgement-ſeat; the adulterated ſpirit from God (the great VVhore) hath ſate and reigned o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all Nations and Kings of the Earth, which hath oppreſſed the Creation, and grieved the good Spirit of God, and made war againſt every appearance of the righteous Seed, and the Lamb hath been ſlain from the foundation of the World; the Dragon hath caſt out his Floods of perſecution after the true woman in all ages, which brings forth the Man-Child (the Heir) whoſe right alone it is to rule the Nations; but the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Earth have been angry (and the great men and chief Captains) at the birth of this Child, and have always ſought its life, even when it was young, as in the days of <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod;</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:42614:4"/>and the Beaſt, Whore and falſe Prophet hath made War with the Saints, and perſecuted, impriſoned and killed them, and the Scriptures are fulfilled, <hi>The Devil ſhall caſt ſome of you into Priſon, and you ſhall have tribulation ten days; The Kings of the Earth have ſet themſelves, and the Rulers take counſel together againſt the Lord, &amp; againſt his annointed, ſaying, Let us break their Bands</hi> (or Meetings) <hi>and caſt away their Cords from us:</hi> If you have ears, hear O ye ſons of <hi>Adam,</hi> and his firſt-born in tranſgreſſion, killers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Worſhip and Sacrifice) the Lord hath you in deriſion, and he will vex you in his ſore diſpleaſure, and break you as with an Iron Rod, and daſh you like a potters Veſſel: Be wiſe therefore now, and fear and tremble before the Lord God.</p>
            <p>Theſe things have been, and have overſpread the Earth, and darkned the Air; the <hi>Whore</hi> hath ſate as <hi>Queen,</hi> and the <hi>true Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> hath <hi>fled</hi> and been <hi>hid</hi> in the <hi>Wilderneſs,</hi> and been in great <hi>ſorrow,</hi> and hath brought forth in ſorrow and great tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in all ages; for the Dragon was alway ready to devour her child as ſoon as it was born; yea, every appearance of God and of his Truth and Way of Righteouſneſs, have been op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, as you may read from <hi>Cain</hi> to this day; but ſtill the Child was caught up to God, and they miſt their end, when they ſaid, This is the Heir, let us kill him, and the Inheritance will be ours; and in the days of <hi>Pharoahs</hi> perſecution of <hi>Iſrael</hi> (which was, <hi>leſt they ſhould multiply and become great in number</hi>) the Midwives feared God, and <hi>Moſes</hi> was born and hid from them, who was appointed to lead <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of <hi>Egypt;</hi> and in the days of <hi>Herod,</hi> when ſo many young children were killed, he was hid from them, till <hi>He</hi> was dead that ſought the young childs life. How great was the Whores and the Devils rage in thoſe Rulers to deſtroy ſo many innocent babes! (the thoughts of which will make our bowels to move that fear the Lord) and in the days of the other <hi>Herod,</hi> chief Prieſts and Rulers, Scribes, Phariſees and Elders, <hi>Herod</hi> and his Men of War ſet him at nought, and mockt him, becauſe he anſwered him not a word to his many Queſtions (and are not we mockt ſo now, when we are becom fools for his ſake whom the Princes of this world never knew?) Conſider theſe things, for God will not belong mocked by <hi>Cain</hi> nor <hi>Herod</hi> neither, but will give every one a
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:42614:5"/>reward according to his doings: And when they had cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him and put him to death, he roſe again, and is yet hid from them; but to his Diſciples he is manifeſt, and is come the ſecond time to ſalvation, and the grave cannot hold him, nor never could, nor never ſhall; for he was before the grave, death or perſecution was, and ſhall reign over it all for ever and ever; and the Whore, Beaſt and falſe Prophet ſhall be caſt into the Lake, and be tormented day and night for ever and ever, and the Lamb and the Saints ſhall rejoice over her with ſongs of tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph, and <hi>Halelujahs</hi> for evermore, <hi>Amen.</hi> Rev. 19.2, 3.</p>
            <p>So now you may read and ſee, that the ſeed of evil-doers, the birth of the fleſh, or ſpirit of Whoredoms, did always per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute the birth that was born of the Spirit, after Gods Image in all ages: And here is now no new thing happened under the Sun, but the ſame controverſie as was between <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel,</hi> though greater ſhall the Work be (then ever) in theſe laſt days: But this is <hi>Cains</hi> and the <hi>Whores Mark</hi> in all ages, and the <hi>Beaſts,</hi> that God and man takes notice of, or knows them by, (<hi>Perſecution</hi> about <hi>Religion, Worſhip</hi> and <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> &amp;c.) as Chriſt ſaid of the <hi>falſe prophets, By their fruits ye ſhall know them, Do men gather grapes of</hi> Thorns, (prickers) <hi>or figs of thiſtles,</hi> Read theſe things in the fear of the Lord God, for they will add to the weight of the Milſtone when <hi>Babylon</hi> ſinks, which day ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtens as a Woman in travel, and the wo muſt come upon all you who are found in <hi>Cains</hi> way, and <hi>Balaams</hi> way, and the Whores way, as you may read <hi>Jude</hi> 11. <hi>ver.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what will ye now do, O ye ſons and firſt-born of <hi>Adam</hi> in tranſgreſſion? God is raiſing a thouſand <hi>Abels,</hi> and <hi>Enoch</hi> is born again, and <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> is come, and the hearts of the children are turned towards their Father, and the hearts of the Father toward the children, and many are leaving the World and the Earth, and travelling toward Paradice the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of God again, where Mount <hi>Sion</hi> is known, and the King ſitting upon his holy Hill: Therefore let not the Heathen rage, nor the people imagine a vain thing, for it is ſo; God is gathering his Seed from the four corners and quarters of the earth, and his ſheep from off all the barren Mountains, where they have been ſcattered in the dark and cloudy day, without
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:42614:5"/>a ſhepherd, and he will feed them himſelf, and the falſe ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pherds ſhall no more make a prey upon them, who have fed themſelves, and cloathed with the wool, and eat the fat, and puſht with ſhoulder and horns till they have ſcattered (and not ſtrengthened) the diſeaſed. Read <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34. And who ſhall diſannul his Decree, or make void his promiſe and purpoſe? The dry bones muſt be raiſed, and become an exceeding great Army, and <hi>Babylon</hi> muſt full; and this is now doing with great noiſe and ſhaking; Read <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37 7, 8, 9, 10. And by the light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Earth with the power and glory of God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.1, 2. Which day is come, and more and more approaching, though you ſee it not who are in the night; it comes like a thief upon you, and will overtake you as a ſnare; for ſo is the day of the Lord come upon all them that dwell in the Earth, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.2, 3, 4.</p>
            <p>Therefore in vain do you ſtrive againſt <hi>God,</hi> O ye <hi>Rulers</hi> and <hi>Teachers</hi> of the <hi>Earth,</hi> who are in <hi>Cains</hi> way, and <hi>Balaams</hi> way; for his marvellous Work and Wonder muſt be brought to paſs, proſper and be perfected through the whole Earth in theſe laſt dayes. It is not your Priſons, Courts, killings, baniſhments or Inquiſitions ſhall hinder or make void God's Eternal Decree, which is eſtabliſhed in the very Heavens: Don't you remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber how the grave could not hold him under whom your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers crucified, and had from Priſon to Judgment in the days paſt, who is now again riſen among us, and is in the midſt of us who gather together in his Name: And this is the Word of the Lord unto you, he is riſen among us called <hi>Quakers,</hi> and is come and coming in ten thouſands of his Saints, to convince the ungodly of all their ungodly deeds and hard ſpeeches which ungodly ſinners have ſpoken againſt him, and to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute his Judgements upon them, (Read <hi>Jude</hi> throughout) and this the whole Earth ſhall know in the day at hand; for our God is riſen to deliver his people, and to lay low the haughti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the terrible ones, and to ſcatter the proud in their imaginations, and to make the Whore nake and deſolate, as a Widow without children and to exalt Truth and Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Juſtice and true Judgement in the Earth, that Judgment and mercy may meet together, and Righteouſneſs and Peace
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:42614:6"/>may kiſs each other, this is God doing; this hath been want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, mercy and juſtice have not been found in the Judgement-ſeats, but falſe judgement, reſpect of perſons, injuſtice and oppreſſion hath met together there; pride, rage, cruelty, vanity, wantonneſs &amp; hypocriſie hath kiſſed each other there; the poor hath been oppreſſed of his Neighbour, and the rich hath had many friends; this the evils under the ſun hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpered and ſpread like a bay-tree, and equity hath been the low tree, and unrighteouſneſs the high tree, exalted over all; the great Whore hath reigned, with the Beaſt and falſe Prophet; the true Woman hath been in ſorrow, the Lamb and the Saints in great tribulations in all ages; but now ſhe is coming up out of the Wilderneſs, leaning upon her beloved, (and not her own underſtanding) and the Lamb and the Saints muſt get the victory, and all coverings and veils will God rent off from the face of all people, and there ſhall be no place of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs nor ſhadow of death wherein the worker of iniquity ſhall hide himſelf; but death and hell muſt be naked, and give up the ſlain that is in them; the Dragon muſt be chained, and the Beaſt, Whore and falſe Prophet muſt be taken, and caſt alive into the Pit or Lake that burns for ever and ever.</p>
            <p>This will be a woful day for you perſecutors, falſe worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, idolaters, whoremongers, hypocrites, unbelievers, fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and abominable, Merchants of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and all you Seamen of <hi>Babylon,</hi> (who hath ſtrengthened her Maſt, and ſpread her Sayle, and traded with her) when ſhe ſhall lie as a wrack in the midſt of the Sea, and ſink like a Milſtone, and be found no more at all; you that have gone ſo often aboard her in the boat of deceit, and drank the <hi>Wine</hi> of her <hi>Fornications</hi> (in the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterious ſealed Cabines of her <hi>VVhoredoms</hi>) which ſhe hath ſet cht from the <hi>Land</hi> of <hi>Witchcrafts,</hi> and gathered from the <hi>Vine</hi> of <hi>Sodom,</hi> and preſt in the <hi>Fat</hi> of <hi>Confuſion,</hi> and held forth in the <hi>Cup</hi> of <hi>Hypocriſie; howling</hi> and <hi>lamentation</hi> will come up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you, fears and amazements will poſſeſs you, when you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the ſmoak of her torment; Alas! alas! ſtanding aloof off for fear) will be your ſong, vvhen you ſhall ſee this great City in one hour brought to nought.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:42614:6"/>
            <p> No fig-leaves will hide in this day, no ſheeps clothing will cover the falſe Prophet, but you muſt all appear in your own likeneſs and image, before him that ſeeth in ſecret, and be ript up, and ſeen as you are before God, Angels and Men, no vizard of Profeſſion ſhall excuſe you from receiving a juſt recompence of reward according to your deeds done in your bodies.</p>
            <p>And this dreadful day is haſtening upon all fleſh, which hath corrupted its way before the Lord; for his own Name ſake, and for his Elect ſeed ſake, (wil he cut it ſhort in righteouſneſs) which hath long groaned and cryed unto him under the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy burdens and cruel oppreſſions of the ungodly, to be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered from the bondage of corruption which hath long over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpread the whole Earth, and to be ſet free in the Paradice of God, in the glorious liberty which is at his right hand, where is joy and pleaſures for evermore, yea durable riches and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, from whence <hi>Adam</hi> was driven into the Earth by diſobedience, and ſo into darkneſs, ignorance and confuſion, having eaten that which was forbidden, and drank of the flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering <hi>Harlots</hi> Cup, which hath ſince become a <hi>great Whore,</hi> and made all Nations drunk, and ſate upon them, and reigned o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them, even Kings of the Earth, multitudes, tongues and languages; and the <hi>Garden</hi> of the <hi>Sluggard</hi> (or ſloathful, wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, drunken ſervant) hath been all <hi>grown</hi> over with <hi>thorns</hi> and <hi>thiſtles,</hi> and <hi>Nettles</hi> have covered the <hi>face</hi> thereof, and the beſt have been as a briar, and the moſt upright as a thorn hedge, pricking, ſtinging, tearing, killing, and warring againſt the Lilly and the Apple-tree, as it ſprung up in all Ages, as it is written, They <hi>all</hi> have lain in wait for <hi>blood,</hi> they hunt every man his brother with a net: Thus it was in <hi>Micahs</hi> days<note n="*" place="margin">Read <hi>Mic. 7.1, 2, 3, 4.</hi> and the Sacrament of the Altar in the Martyrs days, &amp; the Oath of Allegiance in theſe days, &amp; ſee if the net be not found, &amp; the miſchievous deſire wrapt up now among the bryars and thorns, whoſe end is burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note>, which cauſed ſorrow to come upon him in the conſideration and ſence there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; and in <hi>Jeremiah</hi>'s days, <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.26. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And thus it hath been from <hi>Cain</hi> unto this day, perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting about Religion, Worſhip and Sacrifice; but for the Elect ſake (as
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:42614:7"/>I ſaid before) theſe days ſhall be ſhortned (and this is the Word of the Lord unto you all) <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.22.</p>
            <p>Therefore hearken diligently, and hear all ye Rulers, Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors and People of the Earth, who are the ſons of <hi>Adam</hi> in tranſgreſſion, the fall, and conſider well in what ſtate you now are, and what knowledge of God your Creator you have, and ſee whether you are not ſhut out of the Paradice of God, in which man was made a living ſoul, and whether you are not drove into the Earth, even as <hi>Adam</hi> in tranſgreſſion, afraid of God, and hiding your ſelves from his preſence; in which ſtate you have no true reſt but are ſeparated from the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Life and Unity with the Eternal God (in whoſe preſence no worker of iniquity can endure;) therefore doth God in his eternal love call unto you to come out of <hi>Babylon;</hi> and he hath appointed a day of viſitation unto the children of men in all ages, that in it they ſhould ſeek and meet him, by returning every one from his evil ways, and look unto him from whom they have gone a whoring, who is the alone ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Saviour of all them that repent and turn to him with their whole heart, and that is the ſacrifice which he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth of all that make mention of his Name; for it is not a talk or profeſſion of Chriſtianity and godlineſs, that will ſtand in ſtead in the day of death, or in this day, in which the great deeps of the myſterie, root and ground of all things (which have been ſince the foundation of the World) are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, even unto Babes in Chriſt Jeſus, who is the Wiſdom of God, and the Power of God, which none of the Princes of this World knew: I ſay, the ſecrets of the Moſt High are with them that fear him, whoſe dwelling is in him that hath given them a meaſure of that pure diſcerning Life in which <hi>Adam</hi> gave <hi>Names</hi> unto Creatures and Things according to their <hi>natures,</hi> while he was in <hi>Paradice,</hi> before <hi>tranſgreſſion</hi> was, even in this Life, &amp; through this Life is the living God bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing many ſons &amp; daughters to that glory which was with him before the World began, and is drawing with the Cords of his Love (which is ſtronger then death) many followers after him, who cannot be ſatisfied in the <hi>Earth,</hi> into which they were driven by <hi>tranſgreſſion</hi> and <hi>polution,</hi> which is not their true
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:42614:7"/>reſting-place, as it is written <hi>Micah</hi> 2.10. Therefore we (being awakened) are returning toward our Native Countrey, in which we were created in <hi>Adam</hi> before tranſgreſſion or ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was; and we have given up our hearts, minds and ſpirits, bodies and ſouls, to wait upon our God to receive from him ſtrength and power to be tranſlated into his own image and likeneſs, wherein our ſalvation is wrought out with fear and trembling.</p>
            <p>Therefore ye Rulers and people of the Earth, do you pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derouſly weigh, and deeply conſider what you are doing by endeavouring to hinder us in the narrow way of our paſſage to the Heavenly Holy-Land, or Paradice of God's reſt, which he hath prepared for the poor in ſpirit, and tremblers at his Word, who are not ſatisfied with an outward profeſſion or name to live, whilſt not enjoying the eternal inheritance and poſſeſſion of the Life and Subſtance which is at the right hand of God for evermore. In which paſſage we reſiſt no man, or fight with carnal Weapons (for our Warfare is ſpiritual) but are calling to thoſe who are our Brethren in <hi>Adam,</hi> to turn their minds and affections with us to ſeek after our Native Countrey, where our Father is again found and known, and his voice heard, that ſo the Spirit of enmity which came of the Serpent and the Whore, might no longer remain in God's Creation (from whence the ſtrife and contentions, wars and fightings comes) but be caſt into the Lake for ever.</p>
            <p>Why ſhould you thus abuſe your Brethren? or what reaſon can you ſhew to hinder us in the way of our paſſage to our own Native reſt of our weary ſouls, ſeeing we have no other end or aim in our eye, but the price of the high calling of God in Chriſt Jeſus, who is gone before us into Paradice, from whence we were driven by tranſgreſſion, the cloud of ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Read <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59, throughout.</p>
            <p>And though you ſhould yet more grievouſly oppreſs us, and ſmite us, and even put heavier yokes upon our tender necks, or cauſe us to make brick without ſtraw, as our brethren did, yet we cannot but ſigh and groan, and cry to our God (whom we delight to worſhip, though it be in the Wilderneſs) under the grievous burdens of our oppreſſors: For we being awake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:42614:8"/>and quickned from the deep ſleep of ſin and death (which hath covered mankind) cannot but look to the Rock from whence we were hewn, and preſs forward (in the patient ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings through the ſtrait gate and the daily Croſs) into the Heavenly Kingdom and Dominion of the holy God, into which no worker of iniquity or unclean thing can enter. So (whatever you judge of us) we have no other end in all our meetings together, but to wait upon our God, that we might know his Will, and be guided and directed into all truth by his Spirit which he hath ſent into our hearts, and in it to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and ſerve him all the days of our life; and here we find the narrow way and ſtrair Gate which leads into the Paradice of God, (even to the eternal life; but broad is the way, and wide is the Gate that leads to deſtruction) according to the words of our dear elder Brother Chriſt Jeſus; for we having but turned our faces from the Earth toward the Garden of God our true reſting-place, but immediately our Brethren (the firſt-born of <hi>Adam</hi> in tranſgreſſion) like <hi>Cain,</hi> do riſe up in wrath to ſmite us, by whom we are greatly abuſed, impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned and oppreſſed, who will not go in this narrow paſſage themſelves, nor ſuffer them that would; and in as much as in them lieth, they ſtrive to hide the key of true knowledge from their Brethren, and would not have them ſeek that Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty which hath foundations, whoſe Builder and Maker is God, in which only is the eternal ſalvation, peace and quietneſs of the ſouls of the children of men, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.10.</p>
            <p>Surely this muſt needs be of the old Serpent, the beguiler, oppreſſor and deſtroyer of Mankind, and of the great Whore the Mother of Harlots, even the ſame which beguiled and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, tempted and led them out of the Paradice (of God's counſel and preſence, in which is joy and peace for evermore) even the Murtherer from the beginning, which killed the juſt, and let the mind into the Earth, and its delights, pleaſures and vanities, which comes to an end: Therefore the <hi>Croſs</hi> muſt be taken up (which the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> taught us) daily to the earthly affections &amp; things of this World, in which the Prince of darkneſs ruleth; for it is but a <hi>Croſs,</hi> (not of Wood, Stone, Gold or Silver, but the pure Power of God) by which the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:42614:8"/>World and the things thereof are become dead and <hi>crucified</hi> unto us, and <hi>we</hi> unto them; even ſuch a <hi>Croſs</hi> that the earthly minded are enemies to, who can ſet up and wear the Croſs of Wood, Silver and Gold, which is of the Earth, like them that make them and wear them; but this crucifies the World (and all that is in the World is the luſt of the fleſh, the luſt of the eye, and the pride of life) and the whole <hi>World</hi> lies in <hi>wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;</hi> ſo this crucifies the <hi>wickedneſs,</hi> ſlays the <hi>enmity,</hi> which your <hi>Croſſes</hi> of <hi>Wood</hi> and <hi>Stone</hi> never did, but you have been in <hi>enmity</hi> about them, and ſuch things, and yet are in the luſt and pride, enmity and wickedneſs, ſtumbling at the <hi>Croſs</hi> in which the Saints glory is; for by this are the Kings bound in Chains, and the nobles in fetters of iron, even Lord <hi>Eſau,</hi> and all the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> and Dukes of <hi>Edom, Eſau</hi>'s ſtock; and the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil is King over all the Children of Pride: Read this, and tremble all you whoſe ſtate this is; for it is not your talk of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and of his <hi>Croſs,</hi> that will at all avail you, while you ſtick faſt in the driven-out-ſtate, in which you are ſeparated from the enjoyment of his life and preſence, and not returning to the Rock from whence we were hewen, the tryed everlaſting foundation which is laid in <hi>Sion,</hi> by which every mans Works, Words, Profeſſions and Religions muſt be tryed and made manifeſt of vvhat ſort it is; For by this Line of true Judgement, he that ſays he vvorſhips God, or loves God, and yet hates his Brother, is found a lyar; and vve knovv that all lyars are ſhut out of his Heavenly Kingdom, and muſt have their portion in the Luke that burneth vvith the heavy diſpleaſure of God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21 8.</p>
            <p>Therefore I pray you brethren, be you novv vvell adviſed in vvhat you do, act, or ſpeak, and conſider the end of theſe things, &amp; your ovvn ſtate as to God-vvard; for as for us, vve are but ſtrangers in the Earth (as our Fathers vvere) now vve are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvake, &amp; the glory of it is but like a dream, vvithout ſubſtance or ſatisfaction to the immortal ſoul; &amp; vve novv perceive what the captivity of <hi>Babylon</hi> is, and the Whore vvhich hath ſate and reigned over all Nations and Kings of the Earth, and vvhat that night and ſleep vvas in vvhich the Enemy came and ſovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed tares among the good Seed in the field; for vve being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:42614:9"/>toward the Land of the living (following the Light of <hi>Iſrael</hi>) the promiſes of our heavenly Father are fulfilling unto us, where he ſaid, <hi>They ſhall return and diſcern between the precious and the vile, between him that ſerveth God, and him that ſerveth him not; between him that ſweareth, and him that feareth an Oath, &amp;c. and I will return unto them a pure Language, and they ſhall worſhip me with one conſent:</hi> This the Lord is fulfilling among us, whom he hath gathered out of the many unclean Languages and falſe Worſhips, and vain Religions (the Whores Dommions) to worſhip him in the Spirit and in the Truth, for ſuch only he ſeeketh, and they are the true Worſhippers, <hi>John</hi> 4.23, 24.</p>
            <p>Now I queſtion not but you have heard how <hi>Cain</hi> offered ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifie, and yet ſmote and ſlew his brother <hi>Abel,</hi> whoſe blood cryed from the ground againſt him for vengeance; (may you not read this ſomewhat near? conſider it) and God had no reſpect to his offering, who ſlew his brother, but unto his offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing who was the ſufferer, God had reſpect, as he hath at this day, who ſaith, <hi>To this man will</hi> I <hi>look, who is poor and of a contrite Spirit, and trembleth at my word:</hi> Theſe things, and the ground of them you might perceive, if you were but truly awakened from the deep ſleep of ſin and death, and the pleaſures there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, which are but for a ſeaſon; however the Trump of God is ſounding, which ſhall ere long awaken you to judgement; then ſhall you ſee how you have ſtriven againſt the love and mercies of God, and ſlighted the day of your viſitation from on high, and have fought againſt God's Witneſs and Witneſſes, to keep them in the perpetual <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> captivity, and <hi>Egyptian</hi> bondage and darkneſs: Be not deceived any longer, neither flatter with your ſelves, for we are not blind nor mad, or in ignorance and error, as you have ſuppoſed, believed and reported (through which you have reproached and greatly abuſed us, and ſtrengthened the hands of evil-doers, and cruelty againſt us without cauſe) but we are truly awaken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the voice of the Son of God, who hath opened our ears and underſtandings, and that eye, which the Serpent (the god of the World) had blinded; and now we ſee and know, that if any man love the World, or the things of the World, the Love of the Father is not in him, let him profeſs what he
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:42614:9"/>will. The Scribes and Phariſees could ſay much, could ſay, <hi>We have one Father, even God, and we are Abraham's Seed, and never were in bondage, &amp;c.</hi> and kept ſtrict the Sabbath, and faſted, and made long prayers, and paid tythe, and gave Alms, and read <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets words very exactly, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and yet the love of God was not in them, as you may read <hi>John</hi> 8.33, 37, 39, 44. but they were of their Father the Devil, becauſe his Works they did (notwithſtanding their fair covering) and what was that? they perſecuted and kill'd about Religion and Worſhip, as may be read at large in the Scriptures of truth, of the proceedings (in that age) of the Rulers, chief Prieſts, El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and great Profeſſors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore take heed to your ſelves, and to your own ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and do not ſo haſtily judge amiſs of us, nor thus ſpeak e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil of us, nor abuſe and perſecute us, nor ſo grievouſly and cruelly afflict and oppreſs us any more about theſe things, or becauſe we are not altogether like (or conformable) unto you in your ways and traditions, for God will plead with you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it: but rather judge your ſelves, that you are not haſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with us as <hi>Lot</hi> out of <hi>Sodom,</hi> becauſe of the wrath and ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance which is ſwiftly coming upon the World of the ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, which they ſhall not eſcape; for I tell you, and that from the mouth of the living God, That a terrible ſtorm, &amp; dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful hour is at hand, &amp; except you run our race toward <hi>Zoar,</hi> you will be taken and deſtroyed, being found in ſpiritual <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Egypt,</hi> and in the <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> Market-place (of confuſion, ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, ignorance and unrighteouſneſs) out of which the Lord of the Harveſt hath called and gathered us into his Vinyard, where after our faithful labour therein, we receive, enjoy and reſt in the joy of our Lord: And if you are found ſmiting your fellow-ſervants or brethren (like <hi>Cain</hi>) about theſe things, and eat and drink with the drunken (who are drunk with the Whores Cup) and ſay in your hearts, The Lord delayeth his coming, he wil come unawares upon you, and in an hour when you look not for him, and will cut you aſſunder, and give you your portion with unbelievers, abominable, ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and hypocrites, who ſhall be wailing and gnaſhing of teeth for evermore.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:42614:10"/>
            <p> Therefore remember to do as you would be done unto, for that is the Law and the Prophets; and as for Chriſt and his followers, they are not come to deſtroy mens lives, but to ſave them; and let us alone in our journey or paſſage toward the City or Paradice of the living God, who hath called and awakened us, and raiſed up our affections and deſires, which cannot be ſatisfied with dreams, husks &amp; paint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed things, likeneſſes or vain ſhews; for the Spirit of a man we are now come to know, which goeth upward, and are leaving the Beaſtial Spirit that deſcends downward into the Earth; and now we alſo know that none can learn our ſong but they whoſe minds through the patient ſufferings are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed from the Earth; for it's the ſong of the Lamband of <hi>Moſes,</hi> which chuſed rather to ſuffer affliction, then to embrace the Treaſures of <hi>Egypt,</hi> or the pleaſures of ſin, which are but for a ſeaſon; againſt whoſe brethren generation, ſeed and off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring, the Beaſt, the Whore and the Dragon, the falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, Death and Hell, the powers of darkneſs and ungodli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs make War, who ſhall be caſt into the Lake that burns with fire and brimſtone, even under the ſence and feeling of the Eternal Vengeance of the Almighty God) there to be tormented day and night for ever and ever.</p>
            <p>But bleſſed are they who follovv the Lamb, (in vvhoſe mouth is found no guile) vvhitherſoever he goeth or leadeth, through the patient ſufferings, in the love unfeigned, they ſhal reſt in the Land of the Paradice of the Fountain of pleaſures at the right hand of God for evermore, <hi>Amen: Halelujah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And novv hear, O ye Rulers and Teachers (by vvhat flatter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing title ſoever you are called in this Land) of <hi>England,</hi> your nakedneſs is ſeen, as in the day in vvhich you vvere born, and your hypocriſie and deceit God hath found out and diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; therefore be aſhamed and bluſh, and ſtand guilty before him, and repent if there be yet a minute or place left you, and do not ſtrive any longer againſt God, and to cover your ſelves any more vvith the Name of Chriſtianity, vvhile you are in the nature of Heathens, and in the vvay of <hi>Cain,</hi> perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting and impriſoning about Religion and Worſhip; for it is <hi>Cain</hi>'s mark in all ages, and the Heathens that knovvs not
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:42614:10"/>God, as it is written, and you may read it, <hi>Why do the Heathen rage, and the people imagine a vain thing?</hi> (and its in vain for you to ſtrive againſt the Decree and Work of God which he is bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to paſs) Mark, the Ragers are the Heathen that know not God; and theſe are the perſecutors in all ages; theſe are in <hi>Cains</hi> way, as it is written <hi>Wo unto them, for they have gore in the way of Cain, and ran greedily after the error of Balaam,</hi> (mark, wo is their portion;) and is not this your ſtate, ye Rulers and Teachers of <hi>England?</hi> conſider it in the cool of the day, and let God's Witneſs in your Conſciences anſwer.</p>
            <p>For I tell you from God, and proclaim it this day amongſt you, that wo &amp; miſery wil be your end (if ye proceed in theſe things) which is already ſtealing upon you, and will overtake you as an armed man, and as a woman in travel, and you ſhal not eſcape: For do you think to proſper, or ſet up your ſelves by ſtriving againſt God and his marvellous Work and Will, which is to be done in Earth as it is done in Heaven? Do you imagine that your Laws or Decrees ſhall hinder or fruſtrate God's eternal and unchangeable Decree and Purpoſe, which is to finiſh tranſgreſſion, deſtroy the Works of the Devil, and make an end of ſin; and exalt truth and righteouſneſs, the Mountain of his own Houſe and Holineſs, and to eſtabliſh it a top of all Hills, and over all Mountains, which was before the Mountains and Hills were brought forth, over which it muſt be eſtabliſhed; and to fulfil his promiſe made to <hi>Abraham</hi> and to his Seed, which muſt be as the ſtars of Heaven, and as the ſands by the ſea-ſhore for multitude? And will you yet ſtrive to hinder the encreaſe of God's decreed number? or will you limit his Seed that it might not ſpread and repleniſh the Earth, whoſe right it is to inherit the uttermoſt part thereof, and a multitude of the ſea ſhall be converted unto him? Muſt not this be done which was ſpoken of by holy men of God, as they were moved by the Holy Ghoſt? Shall the wicked (which are like the chaff, and makes a mock at the movings of the Holy Ghoſt, or Spirit) diſannul God's determinate Counſel? Can you hinder the courſe of the Stars, or cauſe them to withdraw their ſhining? or number the ſands by the ſea-ſhore, or ſtop the ebbings or flowing of the Ocean? Or can you ſtop the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:42614:11"/>rain, or cauſe it to rain by your power? Will the ice and the ſnow melt at your command? Will the fierce Winds obey your voice when it iſſueth forth of its treaſury, and whirleth up and down the Earth? Or do you know whence it cometh, or whither it goeth? Wil the thunder and lightnings be ſtaid, and the noiſe and brightneſs thereof ceaſe at your command? If theſe things (and the like) you can do, then will <hi>I</hi> confeſs unto you, that you may go on and proſper, and prevail againſt the Heritage of the Moſt High, whom he hath bleſſed with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting bleſſings: But if you are not able to do theſe things, then in vain do you ſtrive to ſet bryars and thorns in battel againſt a conſuming fire.</p>
            <p>For I tell you again in the Name and Authority of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God (the <hi>Jehovah</hi> of <hi>Iſrael</hi>) That if you ſtill proceed in perſecuting his people and dear children, as you have done, he wil daſh you in pieces like a potters veſſel, and confound and ſcatter you with deſtruction upon deſtruction, till you are become as the chaff of the Summer-threſhing-floor, and as the aſhes of the Dunghil, which the Wind driveth away, and your place ſhall be no more found, and your remembrance ſhall be a hiſſing and abhorring to Nations: This is God's Word of Life and Truth unto you,</p>
            <p>Remember <hi>Cain,</hi> the <hi>Phariſees, Aegyptians</hi> and <hi>Sodomites,</hi> whoſe Works you are doing; your Name of Chriſtianity ſtinks before God and men, and is even a proverb of reproach among Nations afar off. The <hi>Phariſees</hi> (who were perſecutors) ſaid they were <hi>Abrahams</hi> Seed, and had one Father, even God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and yet were doing the Works of the Devil (vvho was their Father) ye hypocrites (whoſe ſtate this is) ſhall not God's dread fall upon you? Wil ye not tremble before his pure eye of jealouſie, which beholds all your doings, thoughts and words, though never ſo ſecret? Will you ſtill ſay, is not the Lord a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, no evil can come upon us? Will you untempered-Morter-daubers, promiſe the Wall ſhall ſtand, and the daub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers thereof be eſtabliſhed, when God hath ſaid, The Wall ſhall be no more, nor them that daub it? is there not a lying ſpirit, and deceitful tongue in the mouth of all theſe Prophets whom the Lord never ſent? And are they not crying peace to the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:42614:11"/>wicked (to whom is no peace from God) and preparing war againſt the juſt that cannot put into their mouths? And are not theſe the greedy dumb dogs that never have enough, and cannot bark to awaken the Witneſs of God in peoples conſciences, that they may ariſe from the dead, and ſtand up that Chriſt may give them light and life, in which they may ſee the thief, and be able to withſtand the Robber.</p>
            <p>Did ever Chriſt Jeſus or his Miniſters, Apoſtles or Diſciples, perſecute about Religion or Worſhip, or run to the Prieſts of the Earth to uphold their Miniſtry? Or eaſt men into Priſons for their bellies? or went to Law for tythes, or took treble damages (as you call them) and rob people that did refuſe to hear them, as you have done? Mention one example in all the Scripture, or elſe be confounded for ever, and your tongues cleave to the roof of your mouths for ever: Or were not the Prophets. Apoſtles and Diſciples of Chriſt always ſufferers, and perſecuted and impriſoned for their Teſtimony, and for righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs ſake by the Powers of the Earth, chief Prieſts and Rulers in all ages? Were they not haled out of the Synagogues, and brought before Rulers &amp; Governors, and ſometimes beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en and ſtoned, whipt, and charged to ſpeak no more in the Name of Jeſus? Was not this their portion from the great men and chief Prieſts and Counſells? And yet did not they learn in all Eſtates to be content? But are not you diſcontent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed who caſt ſuch into priſons for fear of loſing your belly-god? And were not they unlearned and ignorant men in the Laws and Languages of the Rulers, chief Prieſts and Doctors? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And had not they <hi>Latine, Greek</hi> and <hi>Hebrew,</hi> that perſecuted and crucified the juſt? And did not Chriſt ſay to his Apoſtles or Diſciples when he ſent them forth to Miniſter, <hi>Behold I ſend you forth as ſheep in the midſt of Wolves; be ye therefore wiſe as Serpents, and harmleſs as Doves; and take no thought what ye ſhall eat, &amp;c, and what is ſet before you, eat, asking no queſtion, &amp;c.</hi> (then not to go to law about the in bellies, if not ask a que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion about ſuch things.) And did not the Apoſtle ſay, ſuch were enemies to the Croſs who minded earthly things, whoſe God was their belly? which cauſed him even to tel of it weeping among the people, and ſaid their and was deſtruction, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:42614:12"/>that grievous Wolves would enter in, not ſparing the people, after his deceaſe; and hath it not been ſo theſe ſixteen hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years? Have not the people been grieved, robbed and ſpoiled by thoſe Wolves that ſoon got the ſheeps clothing (the Apoſtles and Diſciples words) and turned againſt the life and the ſheep, and grieved them; and theſe Chriſt propheſied of before his departure, ſaying, <hi>Falſe Prophets ſhall riſe and deceive many</hi> (and love would wax cold, and iniquity abound, <hi>&amp;c. by their fruits ye ſhall know them; they have the ſheeps clothing, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly ravening Wolves:</hi> Here is the true character of the falſe Prophets and falſe Apoſtles, and by this ye ſhall know them; <hi>Do men gather grapes of thorns, or figs of thiſtles?</hi> Can you expect a harmleſs Life in a grievous Wolf? though he have the ſheeps cloathing, is not his nature greedy, and ravening, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring among the ſheep and lambs? Do his covering change his nature? Hear this, O ye Prieſts and Prelates, Biſhops, and the reſt of your Brood, and conſider and ſee who are the Thorns, and the Wolves, and the greedy Dogs that have never enough, the biters and devourers, tearers and renders of the ſheep, and look about you, and behold your ſelves, and ſee if you live in the life of what you ſpeak, whether your inſide agrees with the ſheeps covering, the Saints words, of which you make Merchandize; for God is renting off all deceitful coverings, and you ſhall appear as you are to the view of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and no hiding-place ſhall be found for the worker of iniquity; though he profeſs and ſay, <hi>Lord, Lord,</hi> yet he is curſed.</p>
            <p>Now if you ſay you are of Chriſt's ſending, let it appear by abiding in his Commands and Doctrine; let us ſee you are ſheep indeed, by your harmleſs life, and your contentedneſs in all Eſtates, not ſeeking the peoples goods and money, but the good of their ſouls, and the glory of God, by bringing forth good fruits in the ſight of men, by which (your Light ſo ſhining) they may glorifie the Lord of Heaven, and leave grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the people by minding your bellies, what you ſhall eat and drink, and wherewith you ſhall be cloathed, <hi>&amp;c:</hi> I ſay, eat of that bread which comes down from Heaven, and don't ſo much mind the earth, but be cloathed with humility, &amp; walk
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:42614:12"/>in love; for he that loveth not, knoweth not God: For the Apoſtles (of Chriſt's ſending) were harmleſs, <hi>We ſeek not yours, but you; I have coveted no man's Gold, or Silver, or Apparel; and we have the Spirit of Love, and of a ſound mind;</hi> (then not an earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but redeemed from it unto God, as Kings and Prieſts to reign over it) ſo if you be not found in this inwardly, as wel as talk of theſe good things with the mouth and tongue out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, we ſhall judge you in the infallible judgement of Chriſt, that you are not ſent of him, but are the contrary, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, of Antichriſt, the grievers, the thorns the raven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, of the ſtock of <hi>Cain,</hi> and linage of the great Whore, My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie <hi>Babylon,</hi> the falſe Prophets, by your fruits you are and ſhall be manifeſted.</p>
            <p>So conſider theſe things ye Rulers and Teachers of <hi>England,</hi> and tremble and quake before the Lord God, and put your mouths in the duſt, and be ſilent; for your covering are too narrow, and your bed too ſhort, and God is ſtretching the line of true Judgement over you, which ſhall daſh you as with an iron Rod, if you wil not be humbled and confeſs you have ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in all theſe things, and repent ſpeedily, and do ſo no more: And this is the Word of the Lord unto you, which wil ſhortly be fulfilled.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Here followeth ſome Queſtions to be anſwered by the Perſecutors, about Religion and Worſhip, who are uſurping Authority over mens Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences in ſuch things which only belongs to God, and are neglecting their own duty and place (in not relieving the oppreſſed, and doing Juſtice, and ex cuting true and righteous Judgement between man and man) but are making it their work to enſnare the righteous, and oppreſs the innocent, and to ſtrengthen the hands of the wicked, &amp; en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage the evil-doers, for which things ſake God will rebuke them,</hi> Pſal. 82 &amp; 83.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu</hi> 1. <hi>PErſecutor,</hi> What is the Devil, of whom the Scripture ſpeaks, that he is a Murtherer from the beginning? <hi>John</hi> 8.44. And where is he now? And how was he a Murtherer from the beginning? And about what did he murther from the beginning? And how doth he work in the hearts of the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of diſobedience? And what are his works, and where are they which are manifeſt, which the Son of God was manifeſted to deſtroy? <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.2. 1 <hi>John.</hi> 3.8.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:42614:13"/> 2. What was <hi>Cain,</hi> of which the Scripture ſpeaks, that he was of the wicked one? 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.12. And what was the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed one of which <hi>Cain</hi> was, if it be not the Devil? And how was <hi>Cain</hi> of the wicked one (or the Devil) if it were not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he perſecuted and ſlew his Brother about Sacrifice and Worſhip? <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8.</p>
            <p n="3">3. What is the great Whore (which is called Myſterie <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi>) of which the Scripture declares, that ſhe hath reigned o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Nations, Kindreds, Peoples, Tongues and Languages and Kings of the Earth, ſeeing ſhe is called the Mother (or origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal) of all Abominations of the Earth, and that in her is found the blood of the Prophets and Saints, and of all that were ſlain on the Earth? What is the Mother of all abominations, if not that Spirit that led out from God, and perſecuted, killed and murthered about Religion and Worſhip? Whether all abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations did not proceed from this Spirit? And whether the Legions be not in that Veſſel where this Murtherer dwells, who is King over all the children of pride? Read <hi>Rev.</hi> 17. and 18. chap. <hi>Job.</hi> 41.34. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 27.1.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Whether the Devil was not <hi>Cain</hi>'s Father, and the great Whore his Mother, ſeeing the Scripture ſaith, he was of the wicked one; and the Phariſees who perſecuted to death about Worſhip and Sacrifice, were of their Father the Devil? <hi>John</hi> 8.44. And in the Whore <hi>(Myſterie Babylon)</hi> was found the blood of all the Prophets and Saints, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and if all the blood of the Saints was found in her, then whether <hi>any</hi> can be found <hi>out</hi> of her, (when dilgent inquiſition is made by the Spirit of the righteous God?) but if none of the righteous blood be found out of her, but all found in her, then vvhether <hi>Cain</hi> and the Devil vvere not of, and in this Myſterie <hi>Babylon,</hi> the great Whore, vvho vvere Murtherers from the beginning about Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice and Worſhip; by vvhom righteous <hi>Abel</hi> vvas killed from the beginning, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.</p>
            <p n="5">5. What is <hi>Cains Mark,</hi> and <hi>Cains</hi> vvay, of which it is
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:42614:13"/>written in the Scripture, God ſet a <hi>Mark</hi> upon <hi>Cain,</hi> (or takes notice of him by ſomething by which he may be known) and <hi>wo unto them, for they have gone in the way of Cain, &amp;c.</hi> Now what is <hi>Cains</hi> Mark and his Way (canſt thou anſwer me?) if it be not perſecution and murthering about Religion and Sacrifice, in the wrath and envy, ſeeing the Scripture ſaith his countenance fell, and he was wrath, and ſlew his brother; and wherefore ſlew he him? becauſe his own Works were evil, and his brothers righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous<note n="*" place="margin">Mark ye that ſwear and compel to ſwear, and impriſon the harmleſs for not ſwearing; your works are evil, for ye tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs the commands of Chriſt Jeſus, whom all are to hear and obey, who ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all;</hi> and they that obey him, their works are righteous, and God doth and will put a differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence between them and you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout theſe things, as it is written, even as between <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abel.</hi>
               </note>: Mark the occaſion of perſecution, and who are the perſecuted, and of whom are the perſecutors, ſeeing <hi>Cain</hi> was of that <hi>wicked one,</hi> who ſlew his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther about Sacrifice (a matter of Conſcience towards God.)</p>
            <p n="6">6. What is the Beaſt (and his mark or image) which carrieth the great Whore which all the World hath wondered after and worſhipped, or bowed down to, ſeeing the Scripture ſaith the Whore ſate upon many Waters, &amp; the Waters were Nations, Tongues, Peoples, Multitudes and Languages, and ſhe reigneth over the Kings of the Earth, who were made drunk with the Cup of her Fornications, and her Merchants were the great men of the Earth, <hi>&amp;c. Rev.</hi> 18.</p>
            <p n="7">7. And whether this Beaſt be not the great red Dragon which carrieth the great Whore, which ſtands ready to devour the Man-child of the true Woman which was fled into the Wilderneſs for a time, times and a half, into a place appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? And whether this Child which the Dragon would devour, be not that Seed of the Woman which was promiſed ſhould bruiſe the Serpents head? And whether this Dragon be not the old Serpent the Devil and Satan, which rules in the hearts of the children of diſobedience, whoſe Head muſt be bruiſed by the Womans ſeed? And whether the Devil do not know he
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:42614:14"/>hath but a ſhort time when this ſeed comes forth to reign whoſe right it is, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Whether this Seed or Child of the Woman (which muſt bruiſe the Serpents head) be not Chriſt, or the appearance of God manifeſt in fleſh among and in his deſpiſed and afflicted people in all ages? And whether the Dragon that would devour it, be not the Devil that rules in the hearts of the children of diſobedience (the falſe Chriſtians) ſtirring them up to perſecute &amp; murther about Religion &amp; Worſhip, ſeeing <hi>Cain</hi> that did ſo, was of the wicked one, the Murtherer from the beginning, &amp; the blood of all the Prophets &amp; Saints is found in the Mother of all abominations, which is carryed (or upheld) by a <hi>Scarlet</hi> co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loured Beaſt; Mark that: <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.3.</p>
            <p n="9">9. And whether the ſpirit of this Beaſt (which carrieth this great Whore) do not go <hi>downward</hi> to the Earth, and feed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the earth, and the things of the Earth, and minds the earth, its pleaſures, pride, covetouſneſs and ambition, and is puſhing with its horns like the falſe Prophets, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34. ruling with oppreſſion and cruelty, and perſecuting and afflicting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Religion and Worſhip, minding honor below, ſtorming and raging for fear of loſing the Devils Kingdom &amp; his works, which the Son of God the true Womans Seed is come to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy (in whom is known the Spirit of a Man which goes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward) but duſt is the Serpents meat, and upon his belly he goes all the days of his life, and no higher; there he feeds, and out of his dark holes he creeps, ſpitting forth his poyſon and venome againſt that which is always caught up to God out of his reach, though he caſt out his fiery-like Floods after the Woman and her Child, and makes war with the remnant of her Seed (which are this day in being) which keep the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments (and have the Teſtimony) of Jeſus: Mark, the Child whoſe Life the Dragon, Beaſt, Whore and falſe Prophet ſeek to deſtroy, is caught up to God out of their reach, and ever was, and ever will be: And this is the Word of the Lord God unto all perſecutors and Earth (both Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Rulers) about Religion, Sacrifice and Worſhip, you
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:42614:14"/>tread the outward Court; the Serpent bruiſeth the heel (mark that) and not the Head; the Head is in the holy City, where the dogs, (the biters) whoremongers and murtherers cannot come; but beware how you ſport with the Veſſels of the Lord, for they are holy that bear them, left the hand-writing on the Wall appear againſt you, and you be ſmitten with a final de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction; <hi>Dan.</hi> 5. throughout, and fear before the God of <hi>Daniel,</hi> who is perſecuted for worſhipping his God at this day among his Brethren, for he was a trembler at God's Word, <hi>Dan.</hi> 10.11.</p>
            <p>So remember you are once more warned, as God's Witneſſe ſhall anſwer on your death-bed; if you go on in <hi>Cains</hi> way, you ſhall have <hi>Cains</hi> portion, baniſhed from God's peace and reſt, with greater puniſhments then you wil be able to bear; and if you are in the Whores way, in which the <hi>Phariſees</hi> was, profeſſing of <hi>Religion,</hi> and making long prayers, and yet perſecuting about it, you muſt partake of their woes &amp; judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; and if you are in the Beaſts, Dragon, and falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets way (and <hi>Balaams</hi> way) minding earthly things, gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of filthy lucre, caſting into priſons (for your bellies, pride, covetouſneſſe and Earthly Honors ſake) the innocent follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the Lamb (the true Womans Seed) that keeps Chriſts commands, you muſt be caſt into the Lake of fire in Gods wrath and vengeance to be tormented for ever and ever, as it is written, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.19: 20. &amp; 20.10. &amp; 14.19, 20. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Therefore try your ſelves of what birth you are, whether you are of <hi>Cain</hi> or <hi>Abel;</hi> of God or the Devil, of the true wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man (or Church of Chriſt) in deed and in truth, walking in his ſteps, in the ſelf-denial, bearing witneſs for the truth, led from priſon to judgement for the Teſtimony which you hold, and for the word of patience; for this declares his genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.8.</p>
            <p>Or whether you are the Seed of the Adulterers and the Whore, which <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſpeaks of, chap. 57.3. and <hi>John</hi> in the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations,</hi> which drunk the blood of the Saints. Read your ſtate, and ſee who is your Father and Mother, for there is no daubing in God's ſight with untempered morter; you muſt be of the one, or the other; of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> the holy City, or of <hi>Babylon</hi> the great VVhore; the falſe Church or the true you are of; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:42614:15"/>let no man deceive you with flatteries &amp; ſmooth things, for this Teſtimony wil ſtand before God, Angels and men, and J am thus far clear of all your blood, and you will be left without excuſe whether you hear or forbear.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>W. B.</signed>
            </closer>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fear none of thoſe things which thou ſhalt ſuffer. Behold the Devil ſhall caſt ſome of you into priſon that ye may be tryed, and ye ſhall have tribulation ten days. But be thou faithful unto death, and</hi> I <hi>will give thee a Crown of Life,</hi> 
                     <bibl>Rev. 2.10.</bibl>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Have reſpect unto the Covenant, for the dark places of the earth are full of the habitations of cruelty,</hi> 
                     <bibl>Pſal. 74.20.</bibl>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>Matt. 7.15, 16.</bibl> 
                     <hi>Beware of falſe prophets which come to you in ſheeps clothing, but inwardly they are ravening wolves; ye ſhall know them by their fruits.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Do not rich men oppreſs you, and draw you before the judgement-ſeat, &amp;c.</hi> 
                     <bibl>Jam. 2.6, 7.</bibl>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He that loveth his brother, abideth in the Light, and there is none oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of ſtumbling in him; but he that hateth his brother is in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and walketh in darkneſs, and knoweth not whither he goeth, becauſe that darkneſs hath blinded his eyes,</hi> 
                     <bibl>1. John 2.11.</bibl>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For this is the Meſſage that ye heard from the beginning, that we ſhould love one another, not as</hi> Cain, <hi>who was of that wicked one, and ſlew his brother; and wherefore ſlew he him? becauſe his own works were evil, and his brothers righteous. Marvel not my brethren, if the world hate you, we know that we have paſſed from death to life, becauſe we love the brethren: He that loveth not his brother, abideth in death; Whoſoever hateth his brother, is a Murtherer, and ye know that no mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer hath eternal life, &amp;c.</hi> 
                     <bibl>1 Joh. 3.11, 12, 13, 14, 15.</bibl>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:42614:15"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
